Guide to the Japanese Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Japanese lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer collection
1993-2016
MS 2067
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(4 boxes)
The collection consists of fliers, newsletters, brochures, and other educational material published and distributed by Japanese lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer (LGBTQ) organizations, primarily from the Tokyo area. Materials focus on gay and bisexual men's health, sexually transmitted infection (STI) prevention and testing, and community activities for HIV positive individuals. The collection includes publications documenting bars and clubs, community spaces and support services, art and cultural events, and political activism, as well as newsletters from over thirty LGBTQ organizations located in Tokyo and other regions of Japan. Materials date from 1993 to 2016. このコレクションは日本、主に東京首都圏の性的少数派 （ＬＧＢＴＱ: レズビアン、ゲイ、バイセクシュアル、トランスジェンダー、そしてクィア）などの団体によって２０００年代から現在までに配布されたチラシ、ニュースレター、パンフレットなどの収集を目的とする。最初のシリーズにはゲイやバイセクシャルの男性の健康、ＨＩＶなどの性感染症（ＳＴＩ）の予防とテスト、および生活とコミュニティを取り巻く資料が含まれ、広範な内容となっている。それに加えゲイやバイセクシャルの男性に主に焦点を当てたバーやクラブ、コミュニティスペースと支援、芸術や文化イベント、および政治的行動のための出版物で構成されている。第二シリーズは３０以上の東京及び他の地域からで活動しているＬＧＢＴＱ団体のニュースレターが収められる。
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of fliers, newsletters, brochures, and other educational material published and distributed by Japanese lesbian, gay, bisexual, transgender, and queer (LGBTQ) organizations, primarily from the Tokyo area. Materials focus on gay and bisexual men's health, sexually transmitted infection (STI) prevention and testing, and community activities for HIV positive individuals. The collection includes publications documenting bars and clubs, community spaces and support services, art and cultural events, and political activism, as well as newsletters from over thirty LGBTQ organizations located in Tokyo and other regions of Japan. Materials date from 1993 to 2016.
このコレクションは日本、主に東京首都圏の性的少数派 （ＬＧＢＴＱ: レズビアン、ゲイ、バイセクシュアル、トランスジェンダー、そしてクィア）などの団体によって２０００年代から現在までに配布されたチラシ、ニュースレター、パンフレットなどの収集を目的とする。最初のシリーズにはゲイやバイセクシャルの男性の健康、ＨＩＶなどの性感染症（ＳＴＩ）の予防とテスト、および生活とコミュニティを取り巻く資料が含まれ、広範な内容となっている。それに加えゲイやバイセクシャルの男性に主に焦点を当てたバーやクラブ、コミュニティスペースと支援、芸術や文化イベント、および政治的行動のための出版物で構成されている。第二シリーズは３０以上の東京及び他の地域からで活動しているＬＧＢＴＱ団体のニュースレターが収められる。
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Librarian for Japanese Studies, 2016. Materials were collected in collaboration with Yoshie Yanagihara of Tokyo Denki University, Tetsuyuki Shida of Waseda University, and Community Center Akta, a nonprofit organization established for HIV/AIDS awareness.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series: I. General publications, 1993-2016. II. Newsletters, 2008-2016.
Gay men -- Japan; Bisexuals -- Japan; Lesbians -- Japan; Transgender people -- Japan; AIDS (Disease) -- Social aspects; AIDS (Disease) -- Japan; LGBTQ resource
- General publications, 1993-2016; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of fliers, brochures, advertisements, and other publications. Materials focus primarily on gay and bisexual men. Since materials may cover more than one subject, it is recommended that researchers looking for particular types of material examine related topics.
  Arrangement
  Materials are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Academia, 2010–2015 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Advertising, 2011–2016 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arts
    - General, 2005–2015 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Film, 1993–2016 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Community
    - General, 2011–2015 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bars and clubs, 2011–2016 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Pride events, 2010–2015 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Family, 2013–2016 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Health
    - General, 2008–2016 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Sexually transmitted infections (HIV/AIDS)
      - Data/statistics, 2010–2016 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - HIV positive lifestyle, 2006–2016 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
      - Prevention/education, 2007–2015 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Testing services, 2010–2016 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Politics
    - General, 2011–2015 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Ally outreach, 2013–2016 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Social services, 2008–2016 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Travel, 2014–2016 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Newsletters, 2008–2016; Series II
  Series II consists of newsletters and community papers from LGBTQ organizations located in Tokyo and other regions of Japan. The name of the organization that created and/or provided the newsletter are included in the inventory.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by title of newsletter.
  - 2 chome Kawaraban (２丁目振興会), 2012–2014 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - AIDS News Letter (東京都福祉保険局健康全部感染症対策課エイズ対策係), 2013–2015 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Akta: Community Center Akta Monthly Paper (Community Center Akta), 2011–2016 (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Community Center ZEL Freepaper (Community Center ZEL), 2012–2015 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - dista (Community Center dista), Circa 2016 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - fight!! Ehime Gay Community Paper (HaaT えひめ), 2012–2015 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - HANA: Human Associate Nation Associate (Angel Life Nagoya), 2011–2015 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - HOYAKEN: ホヤケン！ 愛媛のLGBT PAPER (Rainbow Pride Ehime), 2013–2015 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - In-Q: Rainbow Culture Magazine (Pinkdot Okinawa), 2013 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - JaNP+: Japanese Network of People Living with HIV/AIDS (日本HIV陽性者ネットワーク・ジャンププラス), 2014–2015 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - JG: 新宿～御苑～四谷 タウン誌 [ジェイジー] (JG -Jumbo Gyoen), 2013–2014 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - LOUD News (LOUD: Lesbians of Undeniable Drive), 2011 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - nankr -okinawa-: Okinawa Gay Community Paper (nankr -okinawa-), 2008–2015 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Nankaidotsushin: 南界堂通信 中高生世代（♂）のライフプランを考える新聞 (MASH Osaka), 2013–2015 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - NA Way Magazine (Narcotics Anonymous), 2011 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - NEST NEWS LETTER (特定非営利活動法人ぷれいす東京), 2012–2015 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - NLGR+: Nagoya Gay and Lesbian Revolution Plus (Angel Life Nagoya), 2011–2015 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Presence Letter (特定非営利活動法人SHIP), 2013 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Pureisu Tokyo Newsletter (特定非営利活動法人ぷれいす東京), 2013–2015 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Regumi Tsushin: RST/ALN れ組通信 (れ組スタジオ), 2012 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Sakura Shinbun: 中高年のためのさくら新聞 (Nankr沖縄), 2015 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - SaL+: サルポジ (MASH Osaka), 2012–2014 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sapporo Gay Life Healthcare Magazine (レッドリボンさっぽろ), 2015 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Sarada (さらだーセクシュアルマイノリティと人権を考える会ー), 2008–2015 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Season: Fukuoka Gay Community Guide (Love Act Fukuoka), 2011–2015 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - SHIP ニュースレター (特定非営利活動法人SHIP), 2014 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Shizuku: しずく新宿ボランティア・市民活動情報誌 (社会福祉法人新宿区社会福祉協議会ボランティア・市民活動センター), 2013–2015 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - SPEAK OUT (Love Piece Club), 2014–2015 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - STOP AIDS (千葉県健康福祉部疾病対策課), 2015 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - to･be: TOKYO RAINBOW PRIDE Official Magazine (Tokyo Rainbow Pride 東京ラインボープライド), 2013 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - TOKYO RAINBOW PRIDE: Official Guide (Tokyo Rainbow Pride東京ラインボープライド), 2013–2014 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - WHO? Magazine (Tokyo Rainbow Week), 2014 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Yaro pegi (Community Center Akta), 2013–2015 (Box 4, Folder 21)